great hello everybody or um my name is
guy sings doc and this is where Gingka
and this is a some of you and already
maybe and watched the first series of
interviews that we've done but Morgan
uka is a therapist who lives in Berkeley
California and she's an amazing writer
and a it's a hunger for knowledge and
how the psyche in psychology of
attachment and everything interpersonal
and movement psychology oriented she has
a deep hunger for that that I've watched
her for years
take take on subjects in psychology and
write articles just from or her own
interest in their own investigation and
that's and she's been getting involved
in something that I do called circling
which is you could say is a a deep
relational practice and presence and
being present in a relational way with
people and basically have you know rich
deep rewarding and even profound
conversations such that both people are
more more and more rich and I do
trainings with training people how to
circle in circling the infinite there
was a graphic wrist movement that is now
all over the world and so when when are
you and I and that's and we started
connecting on what she does it as a
therapist and what we're doing in circle
sir courting she got really excited
about the implications of that there's
actually a practice that's you know
manifests it can be practiced on
multiple different levels but
essentially that she she least saw that
there's lots of insights to be gleaned
about circling through looking at an
attachment lens and that's there's lots
to be gleaned he was looking at
attachment through his circling lens and
how the two intersect and so she's been
her imagination and her attention has
been really correct by this you know so
I'm I'm excited that this interview and
and they have a conversation where we
can begin to make connections together
in the stuff that she's been working on
yeah well I really appreciate that
context setting and I am so glad that we
could just sit down for the last 15
minutes I'm here on the beach before I
go back home I've been here in Baja for
a week and I got to spend a little bit
of time organizing this project that
I've been working on wanting to
interview you I guess it's a co
interviewer saying but for the last nine
months and Josh too as they either
introduced me to this book attachment
and psychotherapy by David Wallen and
ever since he showed it to me I've been
fascinated by it you know I didn't have
when I first had this idea that that
circling creates or offers the
experience of attachment of a secure
attachment I I just I saw it and there
are certain ways things that I saw but I
didn't have a lot of elaborations I just
it was more intuition it was a little
there was a little bit of I think
evidence definitely evidence but this
book is described circling in so many
ways and it's really brought it showed
me how you know made me interested and
how did circling evolve in the last 20
years to come to a lot of the same
conclusions that the field of attachment
for adults has also come to the same
conclusions and for example what I
understand is some of the edges that are
evolving right now are not from the
attachment field but rather they're
drawing from other fields of interest
objectivity and relational theory and
also Buddhism and I know that in
circling for example one of the primary
principles is how deeply can we be with
what is and so these ways that David
Wallen is you know describing all these
different principles and aspects I just
been waiting so long to try to organize
the material to present it to you and
this is this today is just a little
introduction to the interviews we're
going to be doing because there's some
pretty complex terms that I want to
understand better that I want to explore
with you and I think that people would
be really interested in some of these
terms so I want to describe what they
are and and so first of all I was Arif I
that to the two audiences that I'm
speaking to here are therapists because
I think that circling will provide for
therapists many of the things that David
wohl is saying we need to do as
attachment therapists we get to we have
to practice you know there's the what
and then there's the how so as to me
circling shows the how and then also I
want to show how people so many people
who are circling are interested in
attachment theory and also many people
have a lot more even experience and
study than I do in the community and I I
just want to be able to offer more you
know more linking up of the concepts and
the terms and give like flesh out the
conversation so this today is just an
introduction to that and if you want I
can just read a few of those concepts
one thing I was just saying about but I
like I like what what you described
about basically noticing they're tuned
to different parts of the universe are
coming not something without knowing
about each other necessarily
and like I just like the fact that you
just noticed that and they're like
something's there
and you've been mining you've been
mining that and I think that that's one
of the one of the things I noticed that
for me I'm I continually find greater
access or connection to deeper truths is
that when multiple perspectives or
fields look at a phenomenon they start
and they cut they maybe leave a
different language trail and they're
reliable to those conclusions but which
is it which is interesting yes
it's that there's independent people
looking at something and coming to very
similar conclusions um yes look I think
points to like the truth value of
something so I just appreciate that that
you've noticed that and that that's
really in place that your interest is
conceit and I also really like what you
said about the what in the how and my
understanding is as a principal method
right always perceives theory and and
I'm saying that because it's been so
interim with the development of circling
and a little bit why I think we're
attachment theory and circling me is it
is we all kind of notice if we really
think about it somebody somebody
embodies or an ax a particular behavior
pattern or a technique or something
before it's distinct in language and
it's so many somebody knows is good oh
there's a there's a cool thing going on
there what is that right and then and
then they abstract the theory out of
what they see in the world so I think
there's something about there's
something about how knowledge comes into
being at least for human beings anyways
as it seems that we enact something we
enact patterns and we know it through
our our actions in our embodiment and
then we can then abstract like in
language those patterns and then when
it's really good theory which is I think
what were what we're aiming to do here
like that if those abstractions are
really well done and well articulated
then you can you can take the then the
theory then begins to feed into the
method and makes it even more precise
and in more tune and and in that
feedback loop is really really important
oh I love I felt so inspired how you
said that and I was just I'm fantasizing
about having a three-way interview with
David Wallen because he lives in Marin
as far as I know and you know that or
wherever he lives we can have a
videoconference I really want to see you
guys talking about this and so
really excited for you to get I imagine
you know I know that you know a lot of
this already but to hear the quotes and
some of the terms and to deepen into
them so but that's something I hope we
can make happen you know invite him into
the interview see you guys discuss what
you just said sounds like aliveness and
that sounds really exciting
yes so well I guess I was trying in the
last few days well here on the beach to
who finds you know to make a kite a
little bit of an overview and we've
already been going for about 15 minutes
so um I want to try to make it succinct
and let's see I think some of the most
important parts of what David Wallen
says is important is there's a there's a
phrase have you heard of this phrase the
stance of the south towards experience
no but I think I think you do too
and so what this so this was these were
new terms to me from this book and the
stance of the south towards experience
and that there are three stances three
basic stances we can be embedded in
experience and we can we can mentalize
which is also a new term to me which I
think should be actually called
perceptual izing because I think that
that word itself can be misleading it's
not just about thinking and we can be
mindful and there's a lot of throughout
the book it's repeated over and over and
different by different people finding
the same conclusions that that
developing the stance our stance of
ourselves towards our experience is a
primary way to heal insecure attachment
and so hitting upon that was one of the
biggest parts of saying whoa wait who
that's what we're doing encircling we're
studying our stance towards experience
and the one of the ways in is through
the nonverbal through gestures and
posture and people who have not I've
seen over and over circling with you for
on and off for five years hundreds of
circles I see people who are sitting
down for the first time circling just
referencing to each other about posture
gesture nonverbal that this is
referencing to us
we're stance it's waking up the embedded
emotional patterns that were laid down
in our earliest experiences what is this
how yeah like things that make sure that
I'm getting it so they say what you're
saying is that there's who is it what
was the name of the person you're
talking about David wollen wall and so
that one is that there's this thing
called
there's making a distinction between our
experience and the neck like our stance
and our the way that we are in
relationship to our experience is that
what you're talking about yes and that
and what I heard is that that the part
of what makes our experience our
experience isn't something that it's
you'd like embed in the distinction that
the experience isn't just something that
happens to us and then we relate to it
but it seems like I would imagine that I
already have a stance in my experience
whether conscious or unconscious as
you're saying in line he's embedded even
deeper than unconscious that the way
that I stand with my experience affects
my experience yeah that's my experience
it affects my stance I never imagine
there's ways in which that might stance
towards my experience he bends my stance
right ways that notes that open you know
rottenness small transcends that would
get us to the mindful grant the first
one was embedded and this and that so
that's when sorry good mentalizing and
you're saying that it's actually more
accurate to talk
talk about it is a perceiving stance and
then a mindful stance mm-hmm I mean I
don't want to step on I don't know how
to pronounce his name actually I think
it's funny he is the man who came up
with the word mentalizing I don't want
to step on his toes but I just want to
offer to the field to consider how were
or or in the circling world for trans
getting it for our purposes we could
change the word for ourselves right so
embedded is when you feel like the
whatever thing is reality and there's no
distance from it and what I think is
fascinating is you can be disassociated
from experience so you're not even in
the experience right so I think that the
degree of mentalizing that capacity
means you're both feeling it and can
reflect on it right because I think so
this first dance of embeddedness which
he says we all do from time to time but
the degree to which we can move into
mentalizing and mindfulness is the
degree to which we are more securely
attached it's a both a sign of it and
it's a way to become so the idea is that
secure attachment is not an end in
itself and what I'm reading is that John
Bowlby didn't the man the theorists
philosophers psychologists who coined
the term and developed the theory that
he meant that - that he he was saying
that it's actually a state of being - in
which we then can broaden our
understanding of ourselves and it's the
purpose is to connect with others but
it's the one of the deepest purposes is
emotional regulation that the stance of
the self towards experience allows us to
understand our feelings as as messengers
and but if we're embedded in it then the
feeling is the reality not the message
yes is it fair to say is it fair to say
when I'm embedded in my experience an
example of that would be when someone's
something to me and I get really upset
or triggered is the is the term that we
use a lot like I get triggered and upset
and I get really really angry and then I
have this view of you that you're you
know you're doing something bad to me
and that justifies me getting angry and
being upset with you
but I'm actually like not but so that
would be like an embedded experience or
an example of that I think so yeah
until so a percept like perceiving my
experience or borrowing his terms of
mentalizing my experience would be more
like oh hang on a second I'm really
having a reaction just that just that a
little bit about like oh my there may be
making the distinction between my my
experience of you and my experience of
anger and that there may be a difference
between that and what like in what's
really happening yes like that making
that that deep work more subtle or find
kind of distinction between between
reality and my experience mm-hmm
absolutely and so that's why it's so
clear that's what we're already doing
any circle you drive up into that's what
we're trying to do and I don't know many
other I'm sure there are other contexts
for therapists or people to practice
this I know there are nonviolent
communication I mean there's a lot of
different many many obviously many
people and practices but but I I'm not
aware of one that is so available is an
actual community as a regular practice
becomes a way of communicating in the
world you know it's circling I think
includes non-violent communication and
and adds to it I think it's a more or I
don't know it extensively I'm still
trying to determine that but you know I
think that circling explore is even more
of experience and therefore deepens our
ability to reflect the reflective stance
is another term for mentalizing
well you know either ways I'm looking at
the beach behind you I'm like well it
could lead to the beach like that right
I could keep a good direction and take
him back somebody better hi although
there's a beautiful Sun it was burning
the skin so we decided to I got my 15
minutes for the day
we're securely attached in the shade
okay
so let's see
there's so much so like I said some of
that some of that there's just so much
weight so many ways to elaborate so when
I heard you say is like really tonight
maybe you can elaborate on this a little
bit more of a bold b.o.b is that that's
like saying there's a mic secure
attachment ears right John Bowlby mm-hmm
something that he didn't he can he think
that attachment was an and play is that
what I heard you say there wasn't much
difficult and you you made the
distinction that however the emotional
regulation I that comes through being
securely attached is it what it would
both be say that that that what that
gives but so if I have emotional
regulation right and I can securely I
have people in my life or groups in my
life or a girlfriend or a husband or a
wife and I'm securely attached easy is
that in itself emotionally regulating is
that what you would say
that's the age I thought that throughout
our life
I mean secure attachment I think is a
fluid state
guarantee that you know how to work
through complex problems with the people
in your life so that's why I think that
circle winning teaches specific skills
that parallel emotional regulation and
earning secure attachment about and so I
can read a few of what are considered
what happens with communication that is
collaborative and coherent and this is
this is speaking for the parents but
this is what we do on circling and
that's what I'm gonna just be saying
over and over right obviously so the
first one is that through the
interaction with the child or the circle
II we learn as much as possible about
the child's or the circle leaves
experience their feelings their desires
their needs and their views so that's
the first one learning as much as
possible about the other's experience
there's four parts here the second one
is that we actively engage ins a bull
with the child or the circling each
other during periods when when her sense
this is a quote her sense of self and
others is in flux so that's the idea is
how do we engage with each other when
somebody's triggered like you said how
do we stay with experience instead of
argue
right how do we contact that experience
and then the third one is we the parent
the therapists or circle ease initiate
interactive prepare when disruptions
occur some of these are quotes and these
are on page 193 to 194 in the Wallen
book then the fourth part is really
like this is a brilliant part of
circling that I learned from you upgrade
the dialogue to keep up with the child's
or circle these emerging potential so
encircling this is the edge that we have
a being with what is and being with what
is becoming without pushing for things
to be different than they are yeah it's
all right there those four parts that's
I appreciated what you said because my
periods of my understanding of secure
attachment you know and in being game
personally being in a relationship in
which we have the explicit context of an
understanding about secure attachment
and work on it like consciously and if
that isn't really helpful such that both
people kind of understanding that you
know we pair bond my understanding as
human beings throughout time in all
cultures with few exceptions we all pair
bond that they're thoughtful about the
way our nervous systems work that it
just goes better when we have one person
in our lives
that's we're in it in depicted in this
way in a universe which is completely
ambiguous and improvisational did I have
one relationship that isn't right at one
place that I can go and if I'm you
securely attached to you what that means
is that that I can be myself with you
and then even when I'm being kind of
shitty or a pain in the ass triggered or
I'm scared or something that you respond
to me in in a in a way of total
acceptance and love its unshakable and
then and then I can come to you and be
great I can come to you and be the
trouble that can come to you and feel
insecure and they eat that you are one
place in the universe where I don't have
to think about whether or not I've
accepted your love and I think you go
ahead yeah and one of the things I've
noticed is that is I kind of looking at
it in terms like in the context of a
relationship where we both like I have a
job my girlfriend's name is Brianne like
my job would Brianne is to is is that
when she eats reassurance or she's
anxious is to actually be there for love
like it's a pet is 210
- in the place of like just letting her
know that I love her and I'm right there
and we go right to that place and if we
assure her and her vice versa and the
more confidence that we have in that
happening the more I've come to realize
that relating has at least and in the
context of knocking about has less to do
with what I call the relating before
which was so much further downstream
right of the problems that come from
when were not securely attached and the
arguments and dilemmas that end up
downstream I always thought that like
you need to work out those problems
mm-hmm realizing is that not that I
wasn't at the right location I wasn't
where the relationship was that yes was
before those conversations right in that
there's a place deep in our nervous
systems is pre reflective that's even
pre verbal I would say yeah yeah then
like letting letting each other know
that we're there in a deeply emotional
way way upstream the experience of like
when that secure yes there it's not even
like we're not arguing anymore it's not
even like we don't have problems we're
not arguing exactly we don't have any
problems but it doesn't feel like we
figured out or work through those
problems it feels like we just know
where the relationship is yes I think
when you what you're pointing to is what
could be considered the base that even
when on the surface there's there's a
lot of turbulence that in yourself and
in the field with the person you feel
you feel a security underneath the
turbulence and that's what I think the
agreements encircling are providing that
we even people we're sitting with people
we don't know or we know in the context
of circling so we're all agreeing to
certain principles and practices and to
me I'm I'm wondering and I'm suggesting
that I think that creates that field of
security because I trust
that you're going to perceive me with
positive intent you're gonna perceive my
positive intention and that you're gonna
you're striving to understand me and so
what I think everything you just said
what's most what's really important and
circling in this book is it teaches how
how do we do those things how do you
distinguish between upstream and
downstream and that's what I'm really
excited for people in general and
therapists in particular to practice to
get there's there there are mental and
perceptual representations that we start
to get and so that are very key and I'll
just read a few more things and then
maybe we can start to bring it to a
close and then next week go in-depth
into some of these terms okay so
so many great quotes but still just
trying to give an outline so we're
talking about Oh deal is central our
sense of who we are and so a practice
that provides for the practical process
of attachment healing would be one that
does three things one is it encourages
identification of our subjective
experience so we're really identifying
with the felt experience its body
oriented this is a somatic approach to
healing the second one is it illuminates
and evolves how we feel about our
feelings that's the stance you know can
we accept that we're angry can we accept
that were afraid or are we just fear
are we just anger without any reflection
and the third part is it this process
would help us to effectively express
ourselves and be understood in
relationship and that's what the whole
aim of circling is is to how we express
and are we being understood are you
getting my world and I keep seeing over
and over these outlines that that
describe circling in a nutshell how did
you do that
how did the whole community and you get
to this place maybe you can answer now
maybe we can talk about it later
yeah I I mean this is a big question but
I think but but I think that like it's I
mean really a lot of it has to do with
there's just there's such a profound
sense of a capacity for listening that I
think that an understanding that
circling embodies it goes so far beyond
what I understand to be is like active
listening or even a Pathak listening
that's really grounded I think in a
sense of of giving yourself permission
to be really really really interested in
another person and at the same time be
interested having one piece of attention
really over there and that
same time being aware of like what's it
like for me and how am I being impacted
through the process of listening and
understanding person and one of the
things I realized that that does is it
seems to it seems to it seems to invite
a kind of disclose of space that then
calls forwarded discovery of what what
who you are together and like in one of
those we start to bring language about
like oh how it is really for you it's
not just that you feel sad that there's
for example if they talk about feeling
sad but like that it makes sense that
you feel sad and that ms makes sense
that you feel sad is because of a
background which has a particular
structure that's different than mine
that we can discover together so in
looking through the sadness as we
explore the sadness and then I noticed
my responses to the sadness or reflexes
in relationship to and then I bring that
to language and then you start to
realize like oh actually I'm not sad
about the thing I'm sad about on some
level mm-hmm I look at life in such a
way that it looks
it's worthy of sadness and then we can
go right wow wow wow so it becomes a a
revelatory process that ends up both
people end up being changed by in my
experience and it does create it does
create any deep experience of love and I
don't even know why that exactly why
that is like just sharing an insight
that happens with us and through us
about you creates this experience of
affinity that is just absolutely
stunning and I think I just think I want
to hear what you're gonna say but I
think that that's a perfect place to
start to pause and I mean I cannot wait
to continue this conversation but what
were you gonna say oh yeah there's that
on one level I think you're right I
think that experience
deeply seen and both of us deeply seeing
you and experiencing being you know can
at times profoundly impacted by that
opens up our hearts which input
implicitly in a radical way I would
imagine has a deep attunement and an
effective level at an emotional level
yes right yes I'd like you gotta have
like the conscious you know you could
say that you were perceiving our
experience it's going from background to
foreground subject goes object right on
like a on a cognitive level and
simultaneously what's correlates with
that cognitive like the the the glow of
those cognitions are the effective level
of like the experience of revelation and
discovery and so we learned here that
would you feel like a deep a deep
profound attunement and divinity that
opens up towards the unknown so it's
like simon cade they were moving like
through discovering and no movie unknown
we it feeds back into a deep sense of
security that opens opens us up more
towards the unknown inside someone about
it like and i like like an island and
I've been been you know roughly spilled
thinking about like culture for example
we live in a culture but we're also our
own little cultures each person is our
own little culture so to say and if you
a culture is like an island where the
middle of the island is the most secure
or the most structured or the most
familiar and as you start to move
towards the edge of the island where it
hits the water is where it becomes less
and less familiar ring less informed
until you hit the water which is the
unknown yeah and that you know you to be
if we're not and that you know the
artist or the artist of the ones
culturally speaking that like
exists in the act like right at the edge
right where the unknown starts to become
at like newly articulated through a
video through singing like painting
sculpting you know our
that are live at the edge right and
they're not kind of part they're not
really the necessarily part of the
hierarchy of the structured culture
towards the center but just like a play
with the Beatles like all the innovation
which at the time was just people are
like what is this stuff and now it's the
basis of pop music right it's more
common but yes right yeah it is
stimulates so like eventually what is
new becomes a simulated integrated in
the culture and I think that when we
start to relate at this level that that
the deeper we are the more mindful we
can get of what we don't know and
actually have an affinity towards it
right when we're so we're bringing a new
novelty yeah definitely that's that's
part of the essential practice is what I
got from you and circling is how much
can we be with the unknown so that
description is really important and what
I can't wait to do is flesh out I want
to give you know some step-by-step
processes to consider so I really look
forward to I mean that sister this
relates just to profound thing when you
think about it I think that you can
start to feel you can start to develop a
relationship with the unknown that in
one of security
right but you get the weight to the
unknown like how much ease can you feel
at that edge rather than the tension
like what is there what's happening
what's gonna happen to me like the
physical mental ability to recover that
ease yes I think that is quite profound
mm-hmm thank you so much for being
available right before I have to go to
the airport and I will see you back in
Berkeley really soon that's it
looks low mm bye